A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, RG 5 Program Files, Subgroup Grant Files FA1795
Rockefeller Archive Center
- National Programs and New Initiatives, 2002-2015; 11; 14.43 Cubic Feet 38 letter document boxes
  - Living Cities, Inc., 20100297, 2010 December 13-2014 December 31 (Box 158, Folder 3)
    Grant 20100297, Living Cities, Inc.: The National Community Development Initiative, $3,000,000, to support Living Cities and the Integration Initiative, a multidisciplinary focus on both neighborhood and system transformation in five cities, including St. Paul and Detroit.
  - 8-80 Cities, 2013-47362, 2014 January 1-December 31 (Box 159, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5647
    Grant 2013-47362, 8-80 Cities, $274,400, to support 8-80 Cities in producing a nationwide convening and international trip to facilitate the formation of a civic innovation network among leaders in Knight communities, learning how to execute place-based solutions, attract and support talent and foster opportunity.
  - CEOs for Cities, 20120126, 2012 June 11-2014 June 30 (Box 160, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 5654
    Grant 20120126, CEOs for Cities, $590,000, to upgrade the Knight-sponsored Change By Us and launch it in three Knight Communities to more effectively engage citizens in community-wide programs.
  - Hunter Franks, 2013-47350, 2014 January 1-December 31 (Box 161, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5664
    Grant 2013-47350, Hunter Franks, $59,176, to support various creative placemaking activities, facilitated by Hunter Franks, that will inspire robust engagement and change perceptions of place in Knight communities.
  - Intersect Fund, 2013-43065, 2013 October 1-2014 September 30 (Box 161, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 5665
    Grant 2013-43065, Intersect Fund, $75,000, to launch Lend for Philly with a challenge that leads to micro-finance clubs managed by college students to support local small businesses with micro-loans.
  - National Urban Fellows, 2013-45610, 2013 September 1-2014 July 30 (Box 162, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 5671
    Grant 2013-45610, National Urban Fellows, $70,000, to place a National Urban Fellow at the Knight Foundation.
  - The Municipal Art Society of New York, 2014-48029, 2014 March 1-2015 February 28 (Box 167, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 5823
    Grant 2014-48029, The Municipal Art Society of New York, $250,000. To explore and reimagine the role of civic assets, such as public libraries and parks, in creating successful cities including Knight communities Charlotte and San Jose.
  - Trustees for Harvard University, 20123552, 2013 May 1-2014 April 30 (Box 169, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5837
    Grant 20123552, Trustees for Harvard University, $100,000. To establish a mayoral performance analytics initiative that will use new technologies to connect the use of data analytics to increase community engagement to improve community governance.
  - TED Conferences, LLC, 20110376, 2012 January 1-2013 December 31 (Box 170, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5859
    TED Conferences, LLC, 20110376, $250,000. To advance Knight's technology for engagement strategy by sponsoring TED 2012.
- National Venture Fund, 2001-2009; 12; 9.11 Cubic Feet 24 letter document boxes
  - Mercer University, 20010068, 2001 April 10-2002 April 10 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3184
    Grant 20010068, Mercer University, $245,000 for a three-year evaluation of the 120-block, $9.5 million Central South Revitalization project.
  - The Miller Center Foundation, 2001 April 20-2002 April 20 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3186
    Grant 20010070, The Miller Center Foundation, $200,000 for public education activities related to The National Commission on Federal Election Reform, a bipartisan effort to improve and standardize federal election processes.
  - Hispanics in Philanthropy, 20020283, 2002 May 3-2003 May 3 (Box 72, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3242
    Grant 20020283, Hispanics in Philanthropy, $6,000 for general operating support.
  - Urban Strategies, 20020316, 2002 July 23-2003 July 23 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 3325
    Grant 20020316, Urban Strategies, to create a detailed workplan for the Knight Community Fellows Program, which will train professionals to manage complex community development projects.
  - Charity Lobbying in the Public Interest, 20020410, 2002 December 10-2004 December 10 (Box 78, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 3337
    Grant 20020410, Charity Lobbying in the Public Interest, $250,000 to educate nonprofits and community foundations in at least 10 Knight communities about involvement in public policy initiatives and advocacy.
  - Local Initiatives Support Corporation, 20010277, 2001 September 11-2004 September 11 (Box 79, Folder 5-6)
    Knight File Number - 3393
    20010277, for $4 million to Local Inititatives Support Corporation, for the NCDI 2D, the second decade of the National Community Development Initiative.
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation in the United States, 20010249, 2001 September 11-2004 September 11 (Box 80, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3399
    20010249 for $2.5 milllion to National Trust for Historic Preservation in the United States, for integrated, ongoing assitance in preservation-based community revitalization in Knight Foundation communities.
  - Alliance for Justice, 20030099, 2003 October 1-2005 October 1 (Box 83, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3864
    20030099 for $150,000, Alliance for Justice. To increase foundation's awareness and acceptance of supporting nonprofits' work in advocacy and public policy.
  - The Committee for the study of the American Electorate, 20020309, 2002 May 9-2005 May 9 (Box 83, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 3868
    20020309 for $180,000, The Committee for the study of the american electorate. To develop and distribute research and analysis on trends in voter disengagement in the United States.
  - Communications Leadership Institute, 20040066, 2004 September 14-2005 September 14 (Box 83, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3869
    20040066 for $120,000, Communications Leadership Institute. To build the communications skills of the leaders of six Knight Foundation grantee organizations and to provide technical assistance to the organizations.
  - Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, 20030093, 2003 September 9-2005 September 9 (Box 85, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3879
    20030093 for $200,000, Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law. For a research and public education initiative to analyze the impact of the Voting Rights Act, leading up to the law's reauthorization by Congress in 2007.
  - Long Beach Symphony Association, 20020306, 2001-2004 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - The Manufacturing Institute, 20020451, 2002 December 10-2005 December 10 (Box 85, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 3882
    20020451 for $550,000, The Manufacturing Institute. To expand a program into two Knight communities that assists employer-led business associations in their efforts to coordinate workforce development programs.
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), 20020288, 2002 June 10-2005 December 31 (Box 85, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3883
    20020288 for $2.75 million, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT). To continue the museum loan network for another three years.
  - National Association for the Education of Young Children, 20030087, 2003 September 9-2005 April 30 (Box 86, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 3886
    20030087 for $250,000, National Association for the Education of Young Children. To provide professional development and opportunities for cross-community learning for Knight grant recipients in communities that have identified school readiness and other early childhood issues as funding priorities.
  - New Profit, 20040159, 2004 September 14-2005 September 14 (Box 86, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 3890
    20040159 for $175,000, New Profit, Inc. For a convening of leading social entrepreneurs to help them build alliances and generate new thinking and resources to increase their reach and impact. Includes 8 cds of the conference, "Create Tomorrow Today" in February 2005 (2 copies). Participants include Trabian Shorters.
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 1: How Entrepreneurs across Sectors are Shaping American Communities, David Gergen (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 2: How Entrepreneurs across Sectors are Shaping American Communities, Stephen Goldsmith (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 3: Investing in Transformative Change: Lessons from across Sectors, Elys Cheny, Jon Biotti, Trabian Shorter, and Shari Berenbach (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 4 The Power of Innovation in Shaping the Future, Eamonn Kelly (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 5: Through the Eyes of the Social Entrepreneur - The Big Picture, Rob Waldran, J.B. Schamm, and Gerald Chertavian (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 6: Action Tanking and Tipping Points, Michael Brown (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 7: Choice Points in Funding Innovation for Systems Change, Barbara Kibbe (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - New Profit, 20040159 - Create Tomorrow Today: Video 8: Social Entrepreneurship and the American Dream, Eric Schwarz (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Public Interest Projects, 20030094, 2003 September 9-2005 September 9 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3914
    20030094 for $250,000, Public Interest Projects. For a funding collaborative that will promote immigrant civic engagement.
  - 9/11 Public Discourse Project, 20050011, 2005 March 15-2006 March 15 (Box 87, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 4096
    9/11 Public Discourse Project, 20050011 for $200,000. To initiate a nationwide public education campaign for the purpose of making America safer and more secure.
  - Alliance for Children and Families, 20040128, 2004 Septemebr 14-2006 September 14 (Box 88, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4097
    Alliance for Children and Families, 20040128, $300,000. For a series of regional and national scenario planning sessions with nonprofit agencies serving children and families to build their capacity to respond to changing market forces.
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research, 20040063, 2004 September 14-2006 September 14 (Box 88, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4098
    American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research, 20040063, $55,000. For a series of election-year public events encouraging the examination of the governing styles of the major presidential candidates.
  - The Brookings Institution, 20030055, 2003 June 10-2006 June 10 (Box 89, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4101
    The Brookings Institution, 20030055, $500,000. To launch the Neighborhood Markets Project that will collect data on local markets and revenue flows to be used to drive commercial investment in urban neighborhoods.
  - Guidestar, 20050016, 2005 March 1-2006 March 1 (Box 92, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4107
    Guidestar, 20050016, $250,000. For consortium support of Guidestar, a national database facilitating public access to information concerning the operations and finances of nonprofit organizations.
  - Habitat for Humanity of Greater Miami, 20030056, 2003 June 10-2006 June 10 (Box 92, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4108
    Habitat for Humanity of Greater Miami, 20030056, $1.4 million. To build 34 homeownership units in the northeast quadrant of Overtown and form a homeowners association to work on neighborhood issues.
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 20050112, 2005 August 1-2006 August 1 (Box 94, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4114
    Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 20050112, $100,000. Transition funding for the Museum Loan Network (MLN), to stabilize the future of the MLN directory and other museum collaboration programs.
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 20010002, 2001 March 13-2006 March 13 (Box 94, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4115
    National Endowment for the Humanities, 20010002, $2,500,000. To establish a nationwide network of 10 humanities centers devoted to research, cultural preservation, public programming and lifelo
  - National Security Archive Fund, 20030019, 2003 March 11-2006 March 11 (Box 95, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4116
    National Security Archive Fund, 20030019, $1,000,000. For operating support, and to expand access to government documents by increasing use of the Freedom of Information Act.
  - New Profit Inc., 20050113, 2005 August 1-2006 August 1 (Box 95, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4117
    New Profit Inc., 20050113, $250,000. To develop the Social Entrepreneur Action Tank, a new initiative for translating the ideas of top social entrepreneurs into concrete policy recommendations.
  - The Northspan Group, 20030320, 2003 December 9-2006 December 9 (Box 95, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4118
    The Northspan Group, 20030320, $110,000. To develop a comprehensive online source of regional economic data and provide ongoing support for the Arrowhead Business Connection program.
  - One Economy Corporation, 20020449, 2002 December 10-2006 December 10 (Box 95, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4119
    One Economy Corporation, 20020449, $750,000. To expand home access to computers, provide technical assistance and training, and develop local web content to help low-income individuals in Miami and San Jose gain access to services and opportunities.
  - The Urban Institute, 20030053, 2003 June 10-2006 June 10 (Box 98, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4775
    Grant #20030053, The Urban Institute, $1,000, 000. To facilitate electronic filing (e-filing) of IRS Form 990 by nonprofit organization in Knight Communities.
  - ACCION, 20040020, 2004 March 9-2007 March 9 (Box 99, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4241
    ACCION, 20040020. $1 million partial challenge grant to expand micro-lending programs to emerging and established small business entrepreneurs in Knight communities through the introduction of online loan services and through the establishment of two new offices.
  - Leveraging Investments in Creativity, Inc., 20030102, 2003 September 9-2007 September 9 (Box 102, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4243
    Leveraging Investments in Creativity, Inc., 20030102. $800,000 to help create a national network of innovators in the area of artist-driven economic and community development and conduct a limited pilot project in Philadelphia.
  - Living Cities, Inc.: The National Community Development Initiative, 20040113, 2004 June 15-2007 June 15 (Box 103, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4244
    Living Cities, Inc.: The National Community Development Initiative, 20040113. $4.8 million to expand and deepen a tri-sector collaborative investment to improve urban neighborhoods in 23 communities.
  - Manhattan Institute For Policy Research Inc., 20050111, 2005 August 1-2007 August 1 (Box 103, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4245
    Manhattan Institute For Policy Research, 20050111. $100,000 for an immigration reform initiative including research, public communications and legislative policy development.
  - National Center for Family Literacy, 20010226, 2001 June 12-2007 December 31 (Box 104, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4247
    National Center for Family Literacy, 20010226. $1.5 million for a national public awareness campaign promoting family literacy, designed and implemented by the Advertising Council, and to monitor its effects.
  - National Association for the Education of Young Children, 20040108, 2004 June 15-2007 June 15 (Box 104, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4248
    National Association for the Education of Young Children, 20040108. $1.27 million to continue the work of NAEYC's School Readiness Connections project, which provides Knight grantees working in the area of early childhood with opportunities for professional development and cross-community learning.
  - National Executive Services Corps., 20050063, 2005 May 1-2007 May 1 (Box 104, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4246
    National Executive Services Corps., 20050063. $200,000 to enhance general organizational capacity, support affiliate programs in Charlotte and Miami and establish a new affiliate in Tallahassee.
  - University of Maryland, 20040290, 2005 January 1-2007 June 30 (Box 106, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4249
    University of Maryland, 20040290. $100,000 to disseminate research and build constituencies to promote new models for community-based economic development institutions.
  - The University of Maryland, 20050134, 2005 August 1-2007 October 31 (Box 106, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4250
    The University of Maryland, 20050134. $30,000 to identify and assess a range of new state and local policies on community wealth building and asset development, and to make that information available through the Web and other means.
  - Afterschool Alliance, 20050038, 2005 March 15-2008 March 15 (Box 107, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 4460
    Afterschool Alliance, 20050038, $750,000. To provide technical assistance and cross-community learning opportunities to Knight grantees working on out-of-school-time programming and related youth-development initiatives in Akron, Bradenton, Columbia, Columbus, Palm Beach County, Macon and Milledgeville.
  - The American University, 20050069, 2005 June 1-2008 June 1 (Box 107, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4461
    The American University, 20050069, $250,000. To establish the Committee for the Study of the American Electorate at the American University School of Public Affairs Center for Congressional and Presidential Studies.
  - Center for Community Change, 20040112, 2004 June 15-2009 June 15 (Box 116, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4693
    Center for Community Change, 20040112, $1,250,000. To develop a national network of local community-based nonprofit organizations serving immigrant populations that will help them build skills and capacity by linking them to national resources and opportunities.
  - Center for Economic Progress, 20050039, 2005 March 15-2009 March 15 (Box 116, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4694
    Center for Economic Progress, 20050039, $750,000. To support the National Community Tax Coalition in providing intensive technical assistance and cross-community learning opportunities to organizations running Earned Income Tax Credit (EITC)/Prosperity Campaigns in up to 10 Knight communities.
  - Enterprise Community Partners, Inc., 20050109, 2005 August 1-2009 December 31 (Box 118, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 4699
    Enterprise Community Partners, Inc. 20050109, $250,000. To support Green Communities, a collaboration forging closer ties between America's community development and environmental movements.
- Presidential Discretionary, 1997-1998; 13; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - Berea College, 9700211, 1997 December 19-1998 December 19 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1909
    Grant 9700211, $150,000.00, for a Presidential Leadership grant.
  - Carleton College, 9700212, 1997 December 9-1998 December 9 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1916
    Grant 9700212, $150,000.00, for a Pesidential Leadership grant.
  - Claremont McKenna College, 9700213, 1997 December 9-1998 December 9 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1919
    Grant 9700213, $150,000.00, for a Presidential Leadership grant.
  - Colby College, 9700214, 1997 December 9-1998 December 9 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1921
    Grant #9700214, $150,000.00, for a Presidential Leadership grant.
- Transformation, 2007-2010; 14; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Northwestern University, 20070050, 2007 March 12-2010 September 30 (Box 128, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4850
    Northwestern University, 20070050, $639,000, to create an academic program blending computer science and journalism, designed to fill a staffing void at many digital news sites.
  - OneCommunity, 20090028, 2009 March 9-2010 April 30 (Box 128, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4851
    OneCommunity, 20090028, $3,300,000, to provide second year operations for the Knight Center of Digital Excellence, which was created in December 2007 to provide universal digital access in the 26 Knight communities within five years.
  - OneCommunity, 20090095, 2009 March 9-2010 July 31 (Box 128, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4852
    OneCommunity, 20090095, $250,000, to reimburse OneCommunity for using $250,000 of its grant payment to retain New America Foundation for targeted assistance to Knight communities with federal stimulus grant preparation and assessment.
  - Tides Center, 20080031, 2008 March 10-2010 July 31 (Box 129, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4855
    Tides Center, 20080031, $350,000, to help search engines better distinguish between well-reported journalism and everything else on the Internet.
  - Tides Center, 20080035, 2008 March 10-2010 July 31 (Box 129, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4856
    Tides Center, 2008005, $837,000, to enable individuals to create narrowly targeted, local niche publications with local advertising.
- Trustee-Advised, 2015-2016; 15; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - John S. Knight Memorial Journalism Fund Corporation, 2016-52330, 2015 January 1-July 31 (Box 166, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 5816
    Grant 2016-52330, John S. Knight Memorial Journalism Fund Corporation, $50,000. To support the John S. Knight Memorial Scholarship Fund for Akron area college students for excellence in digital journalism.
  - John S. Knight Memorial Journalism Fund Corporation, 2016-52384, 2016 March 7-December 31 (Box 166, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 5817
    Grant 2016-52384, John S. Knight Memorial Journalism Fund Corporation, $20,000. To support the John S. Knight Memorial Scholarship Fund for Akron area college students for excellence in digital journalism.